<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain"> </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <pb facs="#f-172" n="172"/>
            <fw>33</fw>
            <cb/>
            <note type="editorial">Extracts from/summary of <bibl>Conde, Historia de la dominacion,
                  vol. 1, pp. 50-7, 61-6.</bibl></note>
            <ab><!-- possible anchor = stands for when I can use an anchor element to mark the point where the translation starts -->el no recibira nuestros enemigos ni nos faltarà a la fidelidad, ni ocultarà trato
               hostil que entienda: que el y sus nobles pagarán el servicio di un dinar o aureo cade
               año, y cuatro medidas de trigo, y cuatro de cebada, y cuatro de mosto, y cuatro de
               vinagre, y cuatro de miel, y cuatro de aceite; y los siervos o pecheros la mitad de
               esto, Fue escrita en cuatro de Regeb, año noventa y cuatro de la Hegira. Testificaron
               sobre esto Otzman ben Abi Abda, Habib ben Abi Obeida, Edris ben Maicera, y Abulcasim
               el Mezeli <note type="translation">[From previous page: that] he will not receive our
                  enemies, nor will he lack loyalty to us, nor will he conceal hostile treatment
                  that he knows about: that he and his nobles will pay tribute of one dinar or gold
                  piece each year, and four measures of wheat, and four of barley, and four of grape
                  juice, and four of vinegar, and four of honey, and four of oil; and the serfs or
                  commoners half of this, This was written on the fourth of Regeb, year ninety-four
                  of Hegira [AH 94, by Islamic calendar]. Otzman ben Abi Abda, Habib ben Abi Obeida,
                  Edris ben Maicera and Abulcasim el Mezeli testified to this.</note>. The messenger
               who went to make this accord was Tadmir himself. The Moors entering the city next day
               asked where was the garrison Tadmir told them Women.</ab>
            <ab><!-- possible anchor -->Abdelaziz next took Sierras de Segura, Bazta, Acxi, Jayen, Elvira y en Garnata, que
               tenian los Judios y en Anticaria y Malaga y otras ciudades de la costa del mar.<note
                  type="translation">Abdelaziz next took the mountains of Segura, Bazta, Acxi, Jaén,
                  Elvira and Granada, which the Jews held, and Antequera and Málaga and other cities
                  of the sea coast.</note></ab>
            <ab>Tadmir ben Gobdas King of East<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> Andalucia.</ab>
            <ab>The Calif sent Muza to restore Taric. Taric &amp; Muza both went against East Spain
               ordering again <!-- possible anchor --> prohibition de robos y pillage con pena de la vida.<note type="transaltion">Prohibition of robbery and pillage on pain of death.</note></ab>
            <ab>Taric went to founts of Tagus. <!-- possible anchor -->Arcabica sierras. Molina y Segoncia, y las vegas y
               campos que riega el Ebro.<note type="translation">Arcabica mountains. Molina and Segoncia, and the fertile plains and fields irrigated by the Ebro.</note> Muza to Sentica &amp; Salamanca Astorica &amp; then along
               the Duero to the east, to Medina Saracusta<note type="editorial">Zaragoza</note> then besieged by Taric. Muza ben Noseir
               took a great fine &amp; left governor Hanax ben Abdala Asenani who built <!-- possible anchor -->a Mezquita y
               una principal Aljama <note type="translation">a mosque and a principal great mosque</note>.</ab>
            <ab>They took Wesca, Turiazona, Calagurra, Ilerda, Tarragona up to m<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi> Anfranc <note type="editorial">i.e. the Pyrenees (Conde has Afranc: France)</note>. Taric
               took Tortuxa, Murbiter, Valencia, Xativa y Denia. Islam at Barciluna, Gerunda y
               Empuria &amp; also into land of <hi rend="underline">Afranc</hi><note type="editorial">France</note> &amp; took Medina Narbona<note type="editorial">Narbonne</note></ab>

            <cb/>
            <metamark/>
            <ab>where fine 7 idol equestrian of silver in a temple. Then to Guf &amp; <!-- possible anchor -->to Galicia por
               Asturica y en Lugidania <note type="translation">through Astorga and into Lusitania</note>. The Calif had a fifth of spoil. They plundred &amp;
               quarrelled so the Calif ordred both Muza &amp; Taric to Damascus. Muza left his son
               Abdelaziz Governor of Spain. Amir.</ab>
            <ab>Muza went to Damascus with great riches &amp; <!-- possible anchor -->400 Varones de las familias regias
               godas who wore on their heads diademas de oro. &amp; golden belts. entrò en Syria 95
               of Hegira. <note type="translation">400 men of the Gothic royal families who wore on their heads diadems of gold and golden belts. He entered Syria AH 95 [713AD].</note></ab>
            <ab>The Calif Walid received him well I mean Taric</ab>
            <ab>Fostat near Cairo = a Tent. Alguf = north. Alquibla = <choice><abbr>S.</abbr><expan>south</expan></choice> Axarkia = <choice><abbr>E.</abbr><expan>east</expan></choice> Algarbe
               West.</ab>
            <ab> Mechtisebes; treasures of provinces</ab>
            <ab>The Calif ordered the death of Muzas sons in Spain. Poor Abdelaziz was at an
               <!-- possible anchor -->Alqueria cerca Sevilla que se llamaba Kenisa Rebina <note type="translation">a farmhouse near Seville, called Kenisa Rebina</note> where he built a Mosque. El Wali
               his Title <!-- possible anchor -->His muger goda Ayela favorecia mucho a los Xtianos<note type="translation">his Gothic wife, Ayela, greatly favoured the Christians</note>. Zeyad ben Nabigat el
               Temimi got him slain head cut off &amp; body buried <!-- possible anchor -->en el patio. 97 of Hegira <note type="translation">in the yard [courtyard or backyard]. AH 97</note>Tadmir
               sent &amp; got protection from the Calif.</ab>
            <ab>Ayub was elected Wali brother of Abdelaziz he moved from Sevilla to Cordoba.</ab>
            <ab>The Governor of Zaragoza Hanax ben Abdala ben Amru ben Hantala ben Fehid ben Kenan
               ben Thalbe ben Abdala ben Thamir Asafei el Senani <!-- possible anchor -->conquistador de Egipto Africa
               Almagreb e de España companero de Muza ben Noseir <note type="translation">conqueror of Egypt, Africa, the Maghreb and Spain, companion of Musa ibn Nusayr.</note>. He built the great Mosque &amp;
               Calat-Ayub. The embalmed head of Abdelaziz carried to Suleiman the Calif, when Muza
               visited him his sons head shewn. <!-- possible anchor -->o Muza conoces esta cabeza. si bien la conozco, la
               maledicion de Dios sea sobre quien asesinó a quien era mejor que el. y se salió del
               palacio lleno de dolor y fallecio de gran melancolia <note type="translation">Oh Musa, do you know this head? Yes, I know it well, the curse [Conde: 'maldicion'] of God be on whoever murdered he who was better than him. And he left the palace full of grief and died of great melancholy.</note>. This Calif built the great
               Mosque of Damascus, with 600 lamps hanging from gold chains. cost 40 chests of 14000
               doblas <note type="translation">gold coins</note> each. Calif Omar charged them. much smoke.</ab>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
