<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_106">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_106.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
         <zone points="1028,435 854,3829 3525,3867 3525,467" xml:id="zone_Page_106_278f6a65-4f31-4cba-a20e-57f92b813045"/><!-- newspaper(half only) -->
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_106" n="106"/>
            <figure type="print" facs="#zone_Page_106_278f6a65-4f31-4cba-a20e-57f92b813045">
               <!-- this is a print, an extract of a newspaper that Gell has included in his notebook -->
               <label>NOTICE.</label>
               <ab><sic>FRiday<note type="editorial">All apparent errors in this passage are in the original.</note></sic> 28<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> the December 1810 in the Royal Theatre of S.<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Carlos a Benefit of
                  Rosa Lourenzani, first Dancer of the Theatre, on to represent by the Society of
                  the same to well accepted Borlet entitled</ab>
               <label>THE HEAD RISCALDATE.</label>
               <ab>Finisched that wether he will have one pompous &amp; new Dancing the composition
                  the Petter Maria Petrelly, that have for the title</ab>
               <ab>The Conquest of the Isle the Bourbon by to Arm Britich.</ab>
               <ab>He shall be adorned the scene &amp; clothes proper to the character. He will have
                  also one great accompanying the Troops.</ab>
               <ab>This action &amp; translate the leafs the Courier the London narration steril
                  that the leafs we to say this glorious event that done so many the honour for
                  Nation Britich, it appear that no give pleace the to fill the time that owe, to
                  last one action pantomime, reasoa for that the Compositor had that to be worth the
                  speech of the, when no let him be true to serve for to enrich this action &amp; to
                  shew sometime the no humanity the men, e the generosity she men other.</ab>
               <ab>The divertisement to give end the Spectacle the third &amp; fourth act the
                  agreable Borlet</ab>
               <label>THE SEVILLA BARBER.</label>
               <ab>This the Spectacle that for the Beneficed he has honour the to offer the
                  respectable Publik, of whom to hope protection.</ab>
               <ab>To begin at 7 óclock.</ab>


               <label>NOTICIA.</label>
               <ab><sic>SExta</sic> feira 28 de Dezembro de 1810 no Real Theatro de S. Carlos em Beneficio de
                  Rosa Lourenzani, primeira Bailarina do dito Theatro, se ha de representar pela
                  Sociedade do dito a bem acceita Butleta intitulada</ab>
               <label>LA TESTA RISCALDATA.</label>
               <ab>Finda que seja haverá huma pomposa, e nova Dança da composição de Pedro Maria
                  Petrelli, cuja tem por titulo</ab>
               <ab>A Conquista da Ilha de Bourbon pelas Armas Britanicas.</ab>
               <ab>Será adornada de scenario, vestiario apropriado ao character, e terá tambem hum
                  grande acompanhamento de Tropas.</ab>
               <ab>Esta acção he extrahida do que nos referem as folhas do Correio de Londres. A
                  narração esteril que as ditas folhas nos dão deste glorioso acontecimento, que faz
                  tanta honra á Nação Britanica, parece que não dá lugar a prehencher o tempo que
                  deve durar huma acção Pantomimica; razão porque o Compositor teve que valer-se de
                  episodios, os quaes quando não sejão verdadeiros, serviráõ para realçar esta
                  acção, e demonstrar ao mesmo tempo a inhumanidade de huns, e a generosidade dos
                  outros.</ab>
               <ab>Dará fim ao divertimento o III. e IV. Acto da agradavel Burleta</ab>
               <label>O BARBEIRO DE SEVILHA.</label>
               <ab>Este he o Espectaculo que a Beneficiada tem a honra de offerecer ao respeitavel
                  Público de quem es[…] protecção.</ab>
               <ab>Principiará ás 7 hor[…]</ab>
               <ab>Na Officina de Simão Thaddeo Ferreira. Com Licença.</ab>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
