<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain">
            <pb facs="#f-100" n="0100"/>
            <figure type="print" facs="xxx">
               <!-- this is a print, an extract of a newspaper that Gell has included in his notebook -->
               <label>NOTICE.</label>
               <ab><sic>WEdnesday<note type="editorial">All apparent errors in this passage are in the original.</note></sic> the 30<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> January 1811 at the Royal Theatre of S.<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Carlos the following
                  entertainment will be exhibitat for the benefit of John Baptista Gianini chief
                  composer of ballets of said Theatre to commence with a grand Symphony, which will
                  be followd by a ballet in three Acts entitled</ab>
               <label>The whimsical party, or the end of importunity.</label>
               <ab>After which one of the mast pleasant farces hether to laid before the Publich
                  will be performd, the whole to terminate by a grand serwies Dance entitled</ab>
               <label>The Templ of Death.</label>
               <ab>Inwich Laurence Lacombe is to dance a grand Solo. His composition is the
                  production of said Giannini who will consider himself truly happy should this
                  small specimen meet the same encouragement which he has so repeatedly experienced
                  from an enlightend audience, for the space of fine years, during which he has had
                  the honour of submitting his compositions before a Nation which a mongst other
                  distinguishd qualities, is admired for its indulgence &amp; for encouraging the
                  feeble effort of those who submit them solves to hs criticism.</ab>
               <ab>The Theatre will be brilliantty lit. &amp; the performance will commence at 6’ o
                  clock.</ab>

   
               <label>NOTICIA</label>
               <ab><sic>QUarta</sic> feira 30 do corrente mez de Janeiro de 1811 a Sociedade do Real Theatro de
                  S. Carlos representará a Beneficio de João Baptista Giannini, legitimo Compositor
                  do dito Theatro, hum agradavel divertimento : abrirá a Scena com huma grande
                  Synfonia, finda esta se exporá huma Dança de meio Caracter dividida em tres Actos,
                  que tem por titulo</ab>
               <label>La conversazione ridicola o sia La fine degl impertinente.</label>
               <ab>Depois se seguirá huma das melhores Farças que estão em Scena, e terminará todo o
                  Espectaculo com huma grande Dança fabulosa, que se denomina <note>nova<!-- this has been added by Gell --></note></ab>
               <label>Il Tempio della Morte,</label>
               <ab>Na qual Lourenço Lacomba dançará hum grande Solo A referida Dança he composta
                  pelo mesmo Beneficiado : elle se reputará assaz feliz se esta sua fraca producçao
                  não desvanecer o conceito que este illustrado Público lhe tem patenteado pelo
                  espaço de sinco annos, em que elle tem tido a honra de compôr para huma Nação, que
                  tem por base animar aos que se expõe sobre a Scena.</ab>
               <ab>O Theatro estará todo illuminado, e principiará ás 6 horas e meia.</ab>
               <ab>Na Officina de Simão Thaddeo Ferreira. Com Licença.</ab>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
