<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_113">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_113.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
         <zone points="-6,97 5,1229 3410,1229 3416,114" xml:id="zone_Page_113_10a8ab55-2b00-420d-bc55-6070d46a3da6"/><!-- view of Gibraltar -->
         <zone points="2328,1191 2295,1289 3416,1338 3400,1229" xml:id="zone_Page_113_3db2e8ee-5f8a-4ccf-a98b-c95aa000c000"/><!-- marginal 1 -->
         <zone points="2159,1289 2132,3835 3427,3862 3421,1311" xml:id="zone_Page_113_85c115e0-97bf-4197-a89a-9c3ef108d6ed"/><!-- marginal 2 -->
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_113" n="113"/>
            <figure facs="#zone_Page_113_10a8ab55-2b00-420d-bc55-6070d46a3da6">
               <note type="editorial_label">Pen and ink drawing: view of <rs type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</rs></note>
               <label><rs type="place" ref="#gibraltar">GIBRALTAR</rs></label>
               <label><!-- in pencil --><rs type="place" ref="#europa_point﻿"><choice><abbr>Europe P<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr><expan>Europa Point</expan></choice>. Europa p</rs></label>
            </figure>

            <ab>Roads on the West side of the hill of <rs type="place" ref="#gibraltar">Gibraltar</rs> to a great height. On the top of the
               rock magnificent views on all sides, &amp; the precipices of the rock itself
               uncommonly steep and bold. Pretty cottage of the Governor on East side. Near <rs type="place" ref="#europa_point﻿">Europa
               point</rs> a flat place entirely covered with stone &amp; uncultivable. Some pretty
               situations for houses. The Commissioners is a beautiful place &amp; beside a large
               garden has green fields within an enclosure, &amp; well wooded.</ab>
            <ab>The English took possession of a small rocky island called <rs type="place" ref="#parsley">Parsley</rs> isl<hi
                  rend="superscript">d</hi> near Apes hill which they have now quitted.</ab>


            <note type="marginal" facs="#zone_Page_113_3db2e8ee-5f8a-4ccf-a98b-c95aa000c000">MIRADOR OR TOCADOR<note type="translation"
               >Balcony/oriel or boudoir</note>, <rs type="place" ref="#alhambra">ALHAMBRA</rs></note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="#zone_Page_113_85c115e0-97bf-4197-a89a-9c3ef108d6ed">In it views of ports very bad but the Arabesques of
               <rs type="person" ref="#bartolome_de_rages">Bartolomé de Ragés</rs> &amp; <rs type="person" ref="#alonz_perez">Alonzo Perez</rs> &amp; <rs type="person" ref="#juan_de_la_fuente">Juan de la Fuente</rs> in <date when="1624">1624</date> are good, some
               call the place the PEINADOR<note type="translation">Dressing room</note>. it was
               repaired &amp; adorned for <rs type="person" ref="#philip_v">Philip V</rs> &amp; <rs type="person" ref="#dona_isabel">Dona Isabel</rs>. In the <date notBefore="1501" notAfter="1600">16 century</date> there was
               here an inscrip Arabic. “In the name of God gracious &amp; merciful. God be with our
               Lord &amp; Prophet Mahomet. &amp; to his people &amp; friends health, &amp; salvation
               infinitas veces. God is the light of heaven &amp; earth &amp; his light is like
               himself. It is like luminar which having many says is himself alone &amp; is lampara
               de lamparas, as if it were a shining constellation, &amp; burned with holy oil
               neither Western nor Eastern, &amp; which burning shines (alumbra) &amp; without being
               touched (sin tocarlo) Es luz sobre luz. And God guide with his light Him that seeks
               it. God gives Proverbs to the nations &amp; God is omniscient in every thing <note
                  type="editorial">WG's partial translation, apparently from Spanish in <bibl>Juan de
                  Echeverría, Paseos por Granada y sus contornos..., 2 vols (2nd edn, Granada,
                  1814), vol. 1, p. 144.</bibl> WG may equally have been using <bibl>Echeverría's 1764 original</bibl>.
                  WG obviously found this passage difficult. Echeverría's text is: 'En el nombre de
                  Dios, que es misericordioso, y tiene misericordia. Sea Dios con Ntro. Sr. y
                  Profeta Mahoma; y á los suyos, y sus amigos salud, y salvacion infinitas veces.
                  Dios es la lumbre del Cielo, y de la tierra, y la lumbre suya es como él; es como
                  luminar, que siendo muchas las lumbres suyas, es uno él: y es lámpara de lámparas,
                  como si fuese constelacion luciente, y que arde con óleo santo, no Occidental, ni
                  Oriental, y que encendiéndolo alumbra y sin tocarlo es Luz sobre luz. Y Dios guia
                  con su lumbre á quien él quiere. Y Dios es dador de los proverbios á las Gentes. Y
                  Dios es sábio en todas las cosas.' A full version, incorporating WG's translations
                  where possible but correcting errors or omissions, would be: <note type="translation">In the name of God,
                  gracious and merciful. God be with our Lord and Prophet Muhammad. And to his
                  people and friends health, and salvation infinite times. God is the light of
                  heaven and earth, and his light is like him; it is like a star, which having many
                  lights, is yet one: it is a lamp of lamps, as if it were a shining constellation,
                  and burned with holy oil neither Western nor Eastern, and shone once lit without
                  being touched[.] It is light on light. And God guide with his light him that seeks
                  it. God gives proverbs to the nations and God is wise in all things.</note></note>
               <metamark>–</metamark> Supposed to have been a MIRAB<note type="editorial">i.e. mihrab, a niche indicating the direction of Mecca.</note> in the time of the Moors, or a
               kind of ORIEL. The hall of Fruits &amp;cc on old foundations says <bibl>Paseos<note type="editorial">Echeverría, Paseos por Granada</note></bibl>: The prison
               of the Sultana <sic>a</sic> Inner bay, it might be of the <rs type="person" ref="#juan_i">mad queen<note type="editorial">Juana I ('la loca': the mad) of Castile, 1479-1555, wife of Filipe I of Castile.</note></rs>, but the grating made <choice><abbr>a<hi rend="superscript">o</hi></abbr><expan>in the year (anno)</expan></choice>
               <date when="1639">1639</date> as appears from a paper in the <rs type="place" ref="#palacio_de_la_contaduria">Contaduria<note type="editorial">Palacio de la Contaduría (the Accountant's Palace, within the Alhambra complex).</note></rs>.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
