<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_170">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_170.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain"> </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_170" n="170"/>
            <fw>35</fw>
            <cb/>
            <note type="editorial">The following are extracts from/summary of <bibl>Conde, Historia
                  de la dominacion, vol. 1, pp. 1-7.</bibl></note>
            <ab><!-- possible anchor here -->Conde. La dominación de los Arabés</ab>
            <ab>de los campos de Yemen. Islam = seguridad y resignation. unde Muslimes. Idolatrous
               antes Mahomad.</ab>
            <ab>Saad ben Ahmed Cadi de la ciudad de Toledo decia que fueran 2 generaciones de Arabes
               in Arabia. One is extinct tribes of Ad, of Themud, Tesm y Jadis. Los que permanecen
               son dos castas de Cahtan y Adnan. el imperio estaba en la cabila o tribu de Cahtan. y
               la familia de los Reyes Homiares. Kings Lords y <hi rend="underline">Tobeos</hi>.
               Campiñas di Irak o Caldea.</ab>
            <ab>Homiar tribu adoraba el sol, Canenah a la Luna. Misam la estrella Aldebaran. Laham y
               Jedam, Jupiter Estrella. Tay la constellacion de Sohail. Kais la Ashera al Obur. Asad
               la de Mercurio. Tzaquif un tempillo Alat en las alturas de Nahla. Some believed in ye
               resurrection &amp; some sacrificed a camel or horse on the tombs.</ab>
            <ab>Mahomad naciò en Mecca ciudad del Hegiaz. <note type="translation">Conde, The
                  domination of the Arabs from the lands of Yemen. Islam = security and resignation
                  [i.e. resignación]. whence Muslims. Idolatrous before Muhammad. Saad ben Ahmed,
                  qadi [judge of Islamic law] of the city of Toledo, said that there were 2
                  generations of Arabs in Arabia. One is extinct tribes of Ad, of Themud, Tesm and
                  Jadis. Those who remain are two castes [i.e. lines] of Cahtan and Adnan. The
                  empire was in the tribe [cabila] or tribe [tribu] of Cahtan. and the family of the
                  Himyarite Kings. Kings, Lords and Successors [Conde: 'Tobeos ó sucesores'].
                  Countryside of [Conde: 'de'] Iraq or Chaldea. Himyarite tribe worshipped the sun,
                  Canenah the moon, Misam the star Aldebaran, Laham and Jedam the star Jupiter, Tay
                  the constellation Suhail [Vela], Kais [the star] Ashera al Obur, Asad that of
                  Mercury, Tzaquif a small temple [Conde: 'templillo'] Alat in the heights of Nahla.
                  Some believed in the resurrection [of the dead, not specifically of Christ: Conde]
                  and some sacrificed a camel or horse on the tombs. Muhammad was born in Mecca, a
                  city in the Hejaz.</note> there the Anc<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Temple
                     <sic>Albaram<note type="editorial">Conde has 'Alharam'</note></sic> to true
               God. founded by Ismael. Mahomad of tribe or Cabila de Coraix <note type="editorial"
                  >tribe of Quraysh</note> of great family. Conqueror at Honain at Bedrè &amp;
               Ohod.</ab>
            <ab>Adnan descendant of Ismael</ab>
            <ab>Maad</ab>
            <ab>Nazar</ab>
            <ab>Modhar</ab>
            <ab>Alyas</ab>
            <ab>Modreca</ab>
            <ab>Hozaimah</ab>
            <ab>Kenanah</ab>
            <ab>Alnadhr</ab>
            <ab>Malec</ab>
            <ab>Fehr</ab>
            <ab>Galeb</ab>
            <ab>Lova</ab>
            <ab>Caab</ab>
            <ab>Morra</ab>
            <ab>Kelab</ab>
            <ab><sic>Rosa<note type="editorial">Conde has 'Kosa'</note></sic></ab>
            <ab>Abdmenaf</ab>
            <ab>Hasem</ab>
            <ab>Abdelmotaleb <metamark>X<note type="editorial">i.e. indicating
                  below</note></metamark></ab>
            <ab>Abdalah = Amina</ab>
            <ab>Mahomad = Cadijah<note type="editorial">Khadija, the Prophet's first wife. Not in
                  Conde.</note></ab>
            <ab>Arabs counted from the epoch of the Ethiopic war or “la entrada del Señor del Alfil
               o del Elefante<note type="editorial">the entry of the Lord of the Elephant ('alfil'
                  is Arabic for elephant). Invasion of Mecca by the Ethiopian Christian governor of
                  Yemen, Abrahah al-Ashram, in c.570-1AD.</note>. In this Abdelmotaleb
                     <metamark>X<note type="editorial">i.e. indicating above, Muhammad's
                     grandfather</note></metamark> defended his country &amp; destroyed the army of
               the Ethiopian King. This war mentioned in the Koran. Jusuf ben Said of Illora writes
               about it also.</ab>
            <ab>Medina Yatrib afterwards called Medinatalnabi = city of Prophet.</ab>
            <ab>Mahomed born at dawn 8 of month Rebie primera<note type="editorial">Rabi al-Awwal
                  (month in Islamic calendar)</note> on tuesday 622 after <choice>
                  <abbr>X<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                  <expan>Christ</expan>
               </choice>.<note type="editorial">WG has misread here: Conde says Muhammad was born in
                  572AD, but that Hegira (Islamic calendar) begins in 622AD.</note></ab>


            <cb/><metamark/>
            <note type="editorial">The following are extracts from/summary of <bibl>Conde, Historia
                  de la dominacion, vol. 1, pp. 22-30, 33.</bibl></note>
            <ab>In year of Hegira 86. A<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> X<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                  705<note type="editorial">AH 86, 705AD</note> died the Calif Abdelmelec. His son
               Walid ben Abdelmelic succeeded. He confirmed Muza ben Noseir <note type="editorial"
                  >i.e. Musa ibn Nusayr (c.640-c.716)</note> in command of the troops in Africa, He
               &amp; his son Abdelaziz conquered in Almagreb. beat the Moor tribes Masmuda. Zanhaga.
               Ketama &amp; Hoara. Meruan son of Musa came to Tanja <note type="editorial">i.e.
                  Tangier</note>.</ab>
            <ab><!-- possible anchor here -->Certain Xtians of Gezira de Alandalus ofendida de su
               Rey Ruderic vinieron a Muza ben Noseir, y le incitaron a pasar con tropas a España.
               The channel or gut called Alzacac. El Rey Don Alfonso el Sabio made the chronicle of
               these times but la Caba the Donzella Alifa &amp;c all Moorish fictions. The Calif
               applauded Muzas enterprise. Muza sent Taric ben Zeyad. He passed with quinientos
               caballeros Arabes en 4 barcos grandes a<hi rend="superscript">o</hi> 710 <note
                  type="translation">Certain Christians of Gezira of al-Andalus [Conde's
                  translation: the peninsula of Spain], offended by their King Ruderic, came to Musa
                  ibn Nusayr and incited him to cross with troops into Spain. The channel or gut
                  called Alzacac. King Don Alfonso the Wise made the chronicle of these times but la
                  Caba, the maiden [Conde has 'doncella'] Alifa etc all Moorish fictions [Conde,
                  vol. 1, p. 25: part of story of why the Arabs crossed to Spain; la Caba, daughter
                  of Count Don Julian]. The Calif applauded Musa's enterprise. Musa sent Taric ben
                  Zeyad. He passed with four hundred Arab knights in 4 large ships in 710AD.</note>.
               They took some places on the coast of Andalucia. &amp; returned.</ab>
            <ab>After this Taric landed with an army at Gezira Alhadra or Isla Verde<note
                  type="translation">Green Island</note>. Taric beat the natives &amp; fortified
               Gebal Taric Alfeth anciently. &amp; burnt his Ships. Tadmir, Roderics captain there.
               He wrote to Roderic. <!-- possible anchor here -->Señor aqui han llegado gentes
               enemigas de la parte de Africa. yo no se si del cielo u de la tierra: yo me halle
               acometido de ellos de improviso: resisti con todas mis fuerzas para defender la
               entrada: pero me fue forzoso cedar a la muchedumbre y al impetu suyo, ahora a mi
               pesar acampan en nuestra tierra: ruegoos Señor, pues tanto os cumple que vengais a
               socorrernos con la mayor diligencia. y con cuanta gente se pueda allegar: venid vos
               Senor en persona que sera lo mejor.”<note type="translation">My lord, enemy peoples
                  from Africa have arrived here. I do not know if from heaven or earth: I found
                  myself suddenly attacked by them: I resisted with all my strength to defend
                  against their arrival: but I was forced to give in to the crowd and their
                  momentum, now in spite of me they camp on our land: I beg, my lord, that it
                  satisfies you to come to help us with the greatest diligence. and with however
                  many people can be gathered: come yourself in person, my lord, which would be
                  best.</note></ab>
            <ab>He sent a fine body of cavalry Gothic who skirmished always with loss. The Muslimes
               commanded by Mugueiz el Rumi.</ab>
            <ab>Roderic raised the whole country &amp; came to</ab>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
