<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_89">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_089.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
         <zone points="27,65 3334,76 3340,957 0,935" xml:id="zone_Page_89_31f6384f-ffff-456a-964d-a5ad09dc3b5c"/> <!-- horses and carriages -->
         <zone points="3051,2502 3051,2605 3280,2605 3280,2496" xml:id="zone_Page_89_f0319239-59ba-42ca-9e7c-d4bdf8c03b50"/> <!-- arch -->
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_89" n="089"/>
            <figure facs="#zone_Page_89_31f6384f-ffff-456a-964d-a5ad09dc3b5c">
               <label>The gigs from <rs type="place" ref="#granada">Granada</rs> to <rs type="place" ref="#malaga">Malaga</rs></label>
               <note type="editorial_label">Pen and ink drawing: horses and carriages</note>
            </figure>

            <ab>In verse in the hall of <rs type="place" ref="#comares">Comares</rs></ab>
            <ab>From the rising to the setting of the sun all Arabia the happy salutes thee, &amp;
               all the universe. This is the high conclave &amp; we are its daughters. truly I have
               preference &amp; the Glory in my race or species &amp; I am the members of the heart
               without any division among them, for in the heart the force of the body &amp; soul
               (spirit) originates.<note type="editorial">This seems to be WG's attempt at the
                  Spanish given in the <bibl>Real Academia de Bellas Artes de San Fernando’s
                     Antigüedades árabes de España. Parte segunda (Madrid, 1804), [hereafter,
                     Antigüedades árabes, vol. 2,] p. 12</bibl>: 'Desde que amenece hasta que
                  anochece te saluda toda la Arabia feliz y todo el universo. Este es el alto
                  cónclave, y nosotras sus hijas; bien que yo tengo la preferencia y la gloria en mi
                  género, y soy los miembros del corazon, sin que haya entre ellos division ninguna,
                  como que en el corazon tiene su orígen la fuerza del alma y del
               espíritu.'</note></ab>
            <ab>another. “Y aunque sean mi adorno los signos de su cielo, con todo se echa en mi de
               menos el resplandor del sol que hace entre ellos. Cubrióme mi glorioso senor Juseph
               con vestida de alegria y primor sin necesitar de otro vestido; y me hizo trono regio,
               cuya altura iguala con verdad a la luz al talamo y al trono celestial.”<note
                  type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades árabes, vol. 2, p. 12.</bibl><note
                     type="translation">And although the signs of his sky are my ornament, yet I
                     miss the radiance of the sun that shines [AA: 'luce', not 'hace'] between them.
                     My glorious Lord Jusef covered me in clothes of joy and beauty without needing
                     other clothing; and made me a royal throne, whose height truly equals the
                     light, the marriage bed and the celestial throne.</note></note> the iron
               balconies placed in 1632. Inscription mentioning the beauty of this hall of the
                  Embaxadores<note type="translation">Ambassadors</note>. <bibl>Antiqüedades arabes.
                  1604.</bibl> O hijo de Rey e descendiente de Reyes y à quien las estrellas en
               alteza no igualan, si a te se comparan! Si edificaste e ilustraste este tan rico
               alcazar, que es singular y de aventajada hermosura; palacio donde se demuestran las
               singulares excelencias de esta gobernacion, que en las escrituras se aclaran. Con el
               la ley de la salvacion ensalzaste en tanto grado que no se puede significcar,
               ilustrandola y a sus sequaces con extrema ventaja de seguridad y honor; por lo qual
               te son a cargo; pues con todos sus vasallos demostras amparo miserecordia justicia
               liberalidad soalzacion clemencia e ninguna crueldad e injusticia” <note
                  type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades árabes, vol. 2, p. 13</bibl><note
                     type="translation">Oh son of a King and descendant of Kings, and whom the stars
                     do not equal in highness, if they are compared to you! If you built and
                     illustrated [or improved?] so rich a fortress as this, which is singular and of
                     outstanding beauty; a palace where the singular excellencies of this government
                     are shown, which become clear in the scriptures. With it you extolled the law
                     of salvation to such a degree that [to say] illustrating [or improving?] it and
                     its minions with the extreme benefit of safety and honour, cannot capture it,
                     for which reason they are in your charge, since with all your [AA has 'tus']
                     vassals you show [AA: 'demostrais'] protection, mercy [AA: 'misericordia'],
                     justice, liberality, solace, clemency, and no cruelty or [AA: 'ni']
                        injustice.<note type="editorial">Translation of 'soalzacion' as 'solace'
                        based on<bibl> Juan de Echeverría, Paseos por Granada y sus contornos..., 2
                           vols (2nd edn, Granada, 1814), vol. 1, p. 121</bibl>, which suggests
                        'consuelo', 'alegria' or 'alabanza' as synonyms for what Echeverría
                        recognises as a rare word</note></note></note><metamark>–</metamark></ab>
            <ab>On another. “Es el Rey Nasere el mayor de los Reyes; de cuya corte salen las
               grandezas de los triunfos, es el adestrador leader<!-- leader in pencil --> con
               poderio y valor, que a todos las naciones pone espanto. Es el que, si en el
               hemisferio se presentase, serian excusados en el los luceros. Es el que a los Reyes
               admira la limpieza de su nacimiento, e a quien los grandes imitan, viendo <hi
                  rend="superscript">x</hi><note type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades árabes,
                     vol. 2, p. 13.</bibl></note><note type="translation">The Nasrid King is the
                  greatest of Kings; from whose court come the grandeurs of triumphs; he is the
                  skilled one with might and courage, who terrifies all nations. It is he who, if he
                  appeared in the hemisphere, the stars would be dismissed by him. It is he who
                  provokes admiration among Kings for the purity of his birth, and he whom the great
                  imitate, seeing... [how admirably he has dispensed his rigour and his clemency
                  with those to whom he owes it]<note type="editorial">WG has corrected to
                     'adestrador', which he translates as 'leader', but <bibl>Antigüedades árabes,
                        vol. 2, p. 13</bibl> does have 'el adestrado' (skilled
               one).</note></note></ab>


            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx"><rs type="place" ref="#court_myrtles">Patio de los Arrayones<note type="translation">Court
                  of the Myrtles</note></rs></note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">Inscriptions of the first court God alone is the
               conqueror. other inscrip in same court. The omnipotence of God Give glory to our lord
               &amp; <rs type="person" ref="#abulhagiagi">King Abulhagiagi</rs> whom god preserve. In the upper gallery an arch of 3
                  varas<note type="editorial">Unit of measurement, explained on pag 190.</note> ½
               lead to a chamber over the vestibule before the palace of <rs type="person" ref="#carlos_v">Carlos 5</rs> was built</note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">The walls of cistern court 24 feet high Castilian. The
               cistern 124 feet high 27 wide 5 deep. the doors of this court are 4 feet ½ broad 8
               high. above the 2 windows God alone is the conqueror.</note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">Aben Hut Almayars arms says Bermudes de Pedraza. Argt
               on a band Sa There is no conqueror but God. sometimes a red hand.<note
                  type="editorial"><bibl>Antigüedades árabes, vol. 2, p. 6</bibl>: 'Aben Hut
                  Alnayar'. Antigüedades Arabes here cites <bibl>Francisco Bermudez de Pedraza, Historia
                  de la antigüedad y excelencias de Granada (Madrid: Luis Sanchez, 1608).</bibl> Aben Hut
                  Alnayar's arms were a black band on a silver field, with letters saying 'There is
                  no conqueror but God'.</note> The antechamber roofed <figure type="in_text"
                     facs="#zone_Page_89_f0319239-59ba-42ca-9e7c-d4bdf8c03b50">
                  <note type="editorial_label">[drawing: arch]</note>
               </figure></note>
            <metamark/>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx"><rs type="place" ref="#hall_comares">Hall of Comaresch</rs><note type="editorial"
               >Comares</note></note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">the kind of work called Comarragia, Niches alternate
               gold blue white &amp; red.</note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">on targets Dese alabanza a solo Dios y. de consiguiente
               dense gracias al mismo Dios<note type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades árabes,
                     vol. 2, p. 10</bibl>.<note type="translation">Give praise to God alone, and
                     therefore give thanks to the same God [or God himself].</note></note>. The hall
               40 feet square by 68. iii. The tiles 1 vara ½ high above this in ovals “o god to thee
               be given honour for ever. &amp; o lord to thee incessant thanks. Give honor &amp;
               glory to the King our Lord <rs type="person" ref="#billah">Abu Abdallah Elgani Billah</rs></note>


         </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
