<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_90">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_090.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
         <zone points="108,87 3443,97 3438,1289 108,1316" xml:id="zone_Page_90_01a3b2f7-92ad-45ec-a497-c9d57a3c47fa"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_90" n="090"/>
            <fw>107</fw>
            <figure facs="#zone_Page_90_01a3b2f7-92ad-45ec-a497-c9d57a3c47fa">
               <note>Pen and ink drawing: landscape</note>
               <label><rs type="place" ref="#pena_enamorados">Peña de los Enamorados<note type="translation">Lovers'
                  Rock</note></rs> near.</label>
               <!-- in pencil -->
               <label>The Moor had a Castle on the top. <rs type="place" ref="#pena_enamorados">Peña de los Enamorados <note
                     type="translation">Lovers' Rock</note></rs> near.</label>
               <label>Story of the Moor against whose <sic>caslte</sic> the Queen came by a
                  miraculous road. He leaped down.</label>
            </figure>

            <ab>The Venta de Archidone<note type="translation">Country inn at Archidona</note>
               rather a good house. bill 5 dollars all but 2 shillings – quit it at 12<hi
                  rend="superscript">h</hi>. <choice>
                  <abbr>L</abbr>
                  <expan>Left</expan>
                  </choice> a large town called <rs type="place" ref="#archidona">Archidone<note type="editorial">Archidona</note></rs> with a
               ruined castle. The plain Arcadian that is the <choice>
                  <abbr>m<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi></abbr>
                  <expan>mountains</expan>
               </choice> rise at once from the flat. Robbers said to be deserters in the country one
               taken up at the corner of our venta<note type="translation">country inn</note> this
               morning. In about an hour, at the end of the plain ascend from it leaving the <rs type="place" ref="#pena_enamorados">Peña de
               los Enamorados<note type="translation">Lovers' Rock</note></rs> L &amp; the river of the
               valley left again of it. Story of an inhab<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> of <rs type="place" ref="#antequera">Antequera</rs>
               running away with his mistress faster than the Justice could pursue on horseback.
               They threw themselves at length from the top. the rock really overhangs. A fine view
               at the top of the vale of <rs type="place" ref="#antequera">Antequera</rs> very large, &amp; the town of <rs type="place" ref="#antequera">Antequera</rs>. the
                  Vega<note type="translation">Fertile Plain</note> very flat several trees. rich in
               corn. <choice>
                  <abbr>Ab<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> 2<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> X</abbr>
                  <expan>About 2pm cross</expan>
               </choice> the river from <rs type="place" ref="#archidona">Archidone</rs>. at 3<hi rend="superscript">h</hi> 40<hi
                  rend="superscript">m</hi><note type="editorial">3.40pm</note> <rs type="place" ref="#antequera">Antequera</rs>. in the
               way stones ancient Roman mark the road in the plain. Antiquera Anticaria large.</ab>


            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">+ quan admirablemente ha dispensado su rigor y
               clemencia con los que debe; entendiendo que en dispensar sus tesoros en esto era la
               posesion que de ellos hascia. Perpetuamente quede sublimado en alteza; a la qual
               todos los Reyes se humillen e teman el furor de la execution de su
               shoulder<!-- shoulder in pencil --> espadla espalda ansi los naturales Moros, como
               los de otra qualquiera nacion.” <note type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades
                     árabes, vol. 2, pp. 13-14.</bibl>
                  <note type="translation">[It is he who provokes admiration among Kings for the
                     purity of his birth, and he whom the great imitate, seeing...] how admirably he
                     has granted his rigour and his clemency to those to whom he owes it
                     [hascia=hacía]; understanding that the possession of his treasures lay in
                     granting them. He remains perpetually sublimated in highness; before which all
                     Kings humble themselves and fear the use [AA has 'execucion'] of his sword,
                     native Moors like those of any other nation. <note type="editorial">AA has
                        'espada' (sword), but WG has confused this with 'espalda' (back or sometimes
                        shoulder), which he has itself corrected from
                  'espadla'.</note></note></note>Another</note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">“Soy estrado carpet<!-- carpet in pencil --> de esposo
               de linda hermosura y cumplimiento. Y si quieres ver la razon de lo que digo mirad la
               hermosura desde mi caliz e avertid en mi corona y tiara; y vereis como es semejante a
               la de la luna. Y Aben Nasëre es el Sol de mi orbe, de rutilante hermosura e ser
               resplandor, luce en alteza de estado, seguro de toda ausencia y apartamiento” <note
                  type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades árabes, vol. 2, p. 14.</bibl>
                  <note type="translation">I am a husband's carpeted room of beautiful loveliness
                     and accomplishment. And if you want to see the truth of what I say, look at the
                     beauty of this [AA has 'deste'] my chalice, and notice [AA has 'advertid'] [the
                     beauty] of my crown and tiara, and you will see how alike it is to that of the
                     moon. And Aben Nasere is the sun of my world, of glittering beauty and radiance
                     [AA has no 'ser']: he shines in highness of status, safe from all want and
                     isolation.</note></note> Another</note>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">ornament<!-- ornament in pencil --> Soy
               decoration<!-- decoration in pencil --> aseo de magnificencia señal y hechura que
               sobrepuja surpasses<!-- surpasses in pencil --> a la felicidad: entendereis ser en
               este mi atavio ornament<!-- ornament in pencil -->, este precioso caliz, alguno que
               esta en pie cumpliendo su oracion. Y todo lo que de el se vacia conviene que luego se
               le reitere; e con mi Señor Aben Nasere ennoblecio dios sus criaturas que procede del
               senor Alhazragi Zahade Aben Obeda.<note type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades
                     árabes, vol. 2, p. 14.</bibl> <note type="translation">I am a washroom of magnificence, a sign and a
                  work that surpasses happiness: you will understand that in this my attire, this
                  precious chalice, is one who is on his feet fulfilling his prayer. And all that is
                  drained from it should later be replaced; and with my Lord Aben Nasere, God
                  ennobled his creatures, who [Aben Nasere] proceeds from Lord Alhazragi Zahde
                  [according to AA] Aben Obeda. <note type="editorial">WG has corrected an apparent printing error in
                  Antigüedades árabes, which gives 'rodo lo que...' rather than
               'todo'.</note></note></note></note>
            <metamark/>
         </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
