<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_199">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_199.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain"> </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_199" n="199"/>


            <fw>4</fw>
            <!-- citation starts here and ends at bottom -->
            <ab>Persians Shiites Ottomans Sunites. At Bagdad &amp; Ispahan the two sects fought.
               Sultan Selim killed 40000 Shiites Contemporary of Henry VIII of England. Francis I of
               france Leo the X. Charles V<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>. Andrea Gritti of Venice
               Doge Wassili Ivanovitch conqueror of Astrachan founder of Russian greatness</ab>
            <ab>2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> Century Omar Ben Abdolaziz the most just sovereign of
               family of Ommia<note type="editorial">i.e. the Umayyad dynasty</note></ab>

            <cb/>
            <ab>Prince Dschem Brother of Sultan Bajazet. who said “there is no blood between Kings”
                  <metamark>–</metamark> the custom being to kill all the younger Sons. Dschem fled
               to Rhodes where the Knights entertained him. They were bought by the Sultan who paid
               40 000<note type="editorial">Quarterly Review has 45,000</note> Ducats a year to them
               to keep him. He got to Nice. then to Chamberry then to Rousillon. Then by Rhone to
               Puy. Here the <choice>
                  <abbr>K<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi></abbr>
                  <expan>Knights</expan>
               </choice> took away &amp; sent back to Rhodes 29 of his attendants. Bajazet offered
               the right hand of S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> John to deliver him up. The prince
               transferred from Castle to Castle. All European Kings tried to deliver him. &amp; the
               Pope tried. The grand master put him in a tower with seven floors. Cellar Kitchen
               Servants 3, 4 &amp; 5 rooms &amp; bed of Prince 6 &amp; 7<hi rend="superscript"
                  >th</hi> for Knights on guard. Charles VIII of france got him sent to the Pope in
                  7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> year of captivity. he embarked at Toulon for
               Civita Vecchia &amp; lived at the Vatican. Charles VIII took him &amp; Pope in <choice>
                  <abbr>Cas<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi>
                     Angelo</abbr>
                  <expan>the Castel Sant'Angelo, Rome</expan>
               </choice> but poisend by the pope &amp; got in dying state to Naples. his body sent
               to Egypt but went to Brusa &amp; buried in Tomb of Amurath 2<hi rend="superscript"
                  >d</hi>.</ab>
            <metamark/>

            <ab>In reigns of Soliman &amp; Salim best time of Turks the greatest commanders by land
               &amp; Sea were apostates from <choice>
                  <abbr>Xtianity</abbr>
                  <expan>Christianity</expan>
               </choice>. Hammer<note type="editorial">Joseph von Hammer, Geschichte des Osmanischen
                  Reiches. </note> gives 8 out of 10 grand Visiers of this epoch.</ab>
            <ab>Wlad &amp; Drakul princes of Wallachia &amp; Bosnia such murderers as surprized even
               the Turks.</ab>
            <ab>But Selim 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> contemporary with Charles IX &amp; Ivan the
               Cruel, S<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> Bartholomews massacre at same time. Fort of
               Wittenstein in Finland taken garrison cut in pieces Commander spitted on a lance
               &amp; roasted alive. This at time that Bragadino governor of Famagusta in Cyprus
               flayed alive by Selim the drunkard who being drunk slipped getting into a bath &amp;
               got a fever &amp; died.</ab>
            <ab>Chaireddin Beglerbeg<note type="editorial">Quarterly Review has 'Begler Beg' [i.e.
                  Beylerbey, Lord of Lords]</note> of Algiers carried off 70 000 of the persecuted
                  moors<note type="editorial">Quarterly Review has 'Morescoes'</note> from Spain to
               Africa. This Chaireddin tried to carry off from Fondi the great beauty Julia Gonzaga
               wife of Vespasiano Colonna Sister of the “divine” Joanna of Arragon painted by
               Raffaelle. She was to have been carried to harem of Turkish Sultan. The sailors of
               Barbarossa disembarked &amp; She scarce escaped nearly naked behind a horseman whom
               She afterwards stilettoed. because “he had dared or seen too much”. In Solymans time,
               The turks played the devil in Fondi for 4 hours &amp; particularly insulted the
               Virgin mary.</ab>
            <ab>Hayreddin or Barbarossas own commentaries give all this<note type="editorial">Gell
                  drafted a novel about the sixteenth-century Ottoman pirate, Hayreddin Barbarossa,
                  about the same time as he was working on these notes: <bibl>American School of
                     Classical Studies at Athens, Gennadius Library, MSS 70.3</bibl>: Sir William
                  Gell, An authentic narrative of the History of Jacub of Jenigawarder and his son,
                  Ariadeno Barbarossa, of the island of Mitylene, in the Aegean Sea, [19th
                  century].</note> He was of Greek descent a Roumelian Sipahi who settled in
               Mitylene at its conquest by Mahomet 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>. His father had 4
               sons the first a Lesbian merchant the 3 others Pirates. Elias the youngest killed
               against Rhodians Urudsch or Horuc &amp; Chisr or Chaireddin Pirates. They took a rich
               french Ship sent it to Sultan &amp; had in return 2 caftans of honour &amp; 2
               gallies. They seized two African towns Budscha &amp; Dscherdshill but fought for
               Algiers against Spain, Then the elder brother Isaac joined Them but he was killed by
               Spaniards storming Kalaatol Kalaat or the Castle of Castles. Kalaatol. Usdruch <note
                  type="editorial">Quarterly Review has 'Urudsch'</note>killed at capture of
               Telmessan but Chaireddin was Beglerbeg of Algiers. Sultan Selim sent him a scimitar a
               horse &amp; a sandschak or investiture. Subdued for Sultan the native princes of
               Tennes &amp; Telmessan.</ab>
            <note type="editorial">Extracted/summarised (with same spellings, order etc) from review
               of <bibl>Joseph von Hammer, Geschichte des Osmanischen Reiches, vols 1-8 (Pest,
                  1827-32), in The Quarterly Review, vol. 49, no. 98 (Jul 1833), pp. 283-322, at pp.
                  288, 299-303, 306-7, 309-15.</bibl></note>


         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
