<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_173">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_173.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain"> </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_173" n="173"/>
            <fw>32</fw>
            <cb/>
            <note type="editorial">Extracts from/summary of <bibl>Conde, Historia de la dominacion,
                  vol. 1, pp. 66-80, 84-92, 98-105, 123-9.</bibl></note>
            <ab>Calif Omar ben Abdelaziz succeeded Suleiman he ordered Aly not to be cursed in
               pulpits.</ab>
            <ab>He deposed Ayub as a son of Muza &amp; made Amir of Spain Alhaur ben Abderahman el
               Caisi. Ayub only governed but well 7 months. Alhaur el Amir went with an army into
               Galia Narbonense que es Tierra de Afranc <note type="translation">Gallia Narbonensis,
                  which is a Land of France</note> a cruel man. Gibal Albortat = the Pyrenees. from
               latin portas<note type="translation">gates</note>. Jezid was next Calif Ahaur deposed
               for cruelty 103. Hegira <note type="editorial">AH 103</note>. next Wali was Alsama
               ben Melic el Chulani, he got to Carcaxona y Tolosa (Thoulouse) <note
                  type="translation">Carcassonne and Toulouse</note>. The Señor de Alfranc<note
                  type="translation">Lord of France (i.e. Charles Martel)</note> here opposed him
               &amp; beat &amp; killed him. Moors retired Ambisa ben Sohim who had been left
               lieutenant sent reinforcements. Abderahman ben Abdala el Gafeki made Amir</ab>
            <ab>The Calif Jezid died for love of Hebaba who was dead. he kept her to look at &amp;
               at last buried her then had her dug up again &amp; died in a few days. aged 33 years
               or 29. Hixem ben Abdelmelic next Calif 105 Hegira <note type="editorial">AH 105
                  (723AD)</note>. Abderahman was deposed &amp; Ambisa became Amir but the deposed
               Amir remained his friend. Ambisa rebuilt the bridge of Cordova visited the provinces
               &amp; gave X<hi rend="superscript">ts</hi> &amp; Muslimes <note type="editorial"
                  >Christians and Muslims. Conde includes Jews.</note> equal justice.</ab>
            <ab>In this time Jews of France &amp; Spain many &amp; rich heard Zonaria their messiah
               was come &amp; went to Syria leaving their goods. He got into France to the Rodans.
               Killed by wounds 106 Heg. 724 X<hi rend="superscript">t</hi><note type="editorial">AH
                  106, 724AD</note>.</ab>
            <ab>He left Hodeira ben Abdala el Fehri who was changed for Yahye ben Zalema. the
               Basques in Alguf montes Albaskenses <note type="translation">Basque mountains</note>.
               changed for Otman ben Abi Neza Amir. Next Amir was Hodaifa ben Alhaus. <sic>nex</sic>
               Otman ben Abi Neza el <hi rend="underline">Chemi</hi>. 109. These Emirs rapidly changed.</ab>
            <ab>Albab in M<hi rend="superscript">es</hi> Albortat = Puycerda <note type="editorial"
                  >i.e. Albab in the Pyrenees (Montes Albortat) = Puigcerdà</note></ab>
            <ab>The Moors arrived at the Garuna. The King of Afranc<note type="translation"
                  >France</note> was Caldus. (Carlos Martel <note type="translation">Charles
                  Martel</note>). Mesaudi calls all French Kings Colorio &amp; Lodorio the Spanish
               Lodron or Odron. Bordhal = Bordeaux.</ab>
            <ab>Medina Towrs = Tours. Moors took it. Hosts met on banks of Owar (Loire). The Moors
               lost the battle &amp; fly to Narbona Medina<note type="translation">Narbonne</note>
               Abderahman being killed.</ab>
            <ab>The moors get into France again under the Amir Abdelmelic ben Cotan 736 X<hi
                  rend="superscript">t</hi><note type="editorial">736AD</note>. next Emir Ocba ben
               Alhegag. he established Cadis <note type="editorial">Conde has 'Cadies', i.e.
                  Cádiz</note>. Abdelmelic became Amir again but was delivered by his own people to
               Baleg &amp; Thaalaba two new adventurers from Africa at </ab>

            <cb/>
            <metamark/>
            <ab>Cordova tied to a stake at end of bridge. They cut off his head. Abderahman ben Ocba
               came to revenge his father. already Thaalaba &amp; Baleg had separated. The son of
               Ocba killed Baleg with his lance &amp; his troops fled. Abderahman had the title of
               Almanzor <note type="editorial">i.e. al-Mansur, the Victorious</note> from this
               Victory. 742<hi rend="superscript">ao</hi>. Hegira 125 <note type="editorial">742AD,
                  AH 125</note>.</ab>
            <ab>The Calif Walid ben Jezid impious drank wine abused power, entered lands of Mecca
               with hunting dogs made good verses &amp; liked music. he was killed 126 <note
                  type="editorial">AH 126, 743AD</note>.</ab>
            <ab>Iusuf el Fehri Amir de España <note type="translation">Jusuf el Fehri, Emir of
                  Spain</note>746. Amer made governor of Sevilla, he descended from Mosab alferez
               del Profeta en la batalla de Bedre. era muy poderoso y habia cōstruido un magnifico
               palacio en Cordoba fuera de sus muros a la parte del ponente de la ciudad y un
               espacioso cementerio. <note type="translation">Mosab, ensign of the Prophet in the
                  battle of Bedre [i.e. Badr, 624AD]. He [Amer] was very powerful and had built
                  [construido] a magnificent palace in Cordoba outside its walls in the Poniente
                  part of the city and a spacious cemetery.</note> Lisbon = Alisbona. Portocale a
               city or port.</ab>
            <ab>Loado seas Senor Dios, dueño de los imperios que das el señorio a quien quieres, y
               quitas el señorio a quien quieres, y honras a quien quieres y humillas a quien
               quieres en tu mano esta el bien y el mal y tu eres sobre todas las cosas poderoso.
                  <note type="translation">Praise be to you, Lord God, owner of the empires, you who
                  give lordship to whomever you want, and take lordship away from whomever you want,
                  and honour whomever you want, and humble whomever you want, in your hand is good
                  and evil, and you have power over all things.</note> &amp;. So begins the reign of
               the Calif Meruan. Forat the Euphrates.</ab>

            <ab>Spain in time of Calif Meruan. under jusuf el Fehri.</ab>
            <ab>Mando restituir los caminos militares de Andalucia a Tolaitola. a Merida, a
               Alisbona, a Asturica, y a Saracusta y Tarracona. Reparò los puentes deribabos las
               Aljamas &amp; con la tercia parte de los productos di cada provincia. La primera
               provincia Andalucia antes Beitica del Beti rio de Cordoba desde su nascimiento. &amp;
               Guadiana contiene Cordoba Esbilia, Carmona, Estija, Talica cerca de Esbilia antigua
               casa real de los Eparcos de España, Sidonia Arcos, Libla, Malaga, Elbira, jayen
               Arjona Castolona, Alturja, Cabra Bulcona (*Porcuna) Astaba Ossona, y otras. 2<hi rend="superscript">d</hi>
               Provincia de Tolaitola antes de Cartagena de las sierras de Guadaramla hasta las
               montañas del otro lado del Duero, contiene Tolaitola, Ubeda, Bayeza, Mentiza,
               Wadiacix. Basta, Murcia, Bocastra, Mula, Lorca, Auriola, Elixe, Xatiba, Denia,
               Lucante, Cartagena, Valencia, Valeria, Segovia, Segobrica Ercabica, Wadilhijara,
               Secunda, Oxima, Colounia, Cauca, Balancia y otras. 3 Provincia de Merida antes
               Lugidania y Galicia Algarbe hasta las costas que baña el mar Britanico – contiene
               Merida Beja, Baracara, Dumio, Alisbona, Portocale, Tude Auria, Luco, Astorica,
               Samora, Iria, <note type="translation">He ordered the military roads to be restored
                  from Andalucia to Tolaitola [Toledo], Merida, Alisbona [Lisbon], Asturica
                  [Astorga], Saracusta [Zaragoza] and Tarracona [Tarragona]. He repaired the
                  demolished [Conde: 'derribados'] bridges, great mosques [etc] with a third of the
                  produce of each province. The first province, Andalucia, formerly Beitica from the
                  Beti, a river in Cordoba, from its source [until it enters the ocean (Conde)]. and
                  [the river] Guadiana [i.e. the region between these two rivers (Conde)] contains
                  Cordoba, Esbilia [Seville], Carmona, Estija [Écija], Talica [Italica] near Esbilia
                  [Seville], the former royal home of the Eparchs of Spain, Sidonia, Arcos, Libla
                  [Niebla], Málaga, Elbira, Jayen [Jaén], Arjona, Castolona, Alturja, Cabra, Bulcona
                  (*Porcuna), Astaba, Ossona, and others. 2nd Province of Tolaitola [Toledo],
                  formerly Cartagena, from the Guadaramla [i.e. Guadarrama] mountains to the
                  mountains on the other side of the Douro, contains Tolaitola [Toledo], Ubeda,
                  Bayeza, Mentiza, Wadiacix, Basta, Murcia, Bocastra, Mula, Lorca, Auriola, Elixe,
                  Xatiba, Denia, Lucante, Cartagena, Valencia, Valeria, Segovia, Segobrica,
                  Ercabica, Wadilhijara, Secunda, Ocxima, Colounia, Cauca, Balancia and others. 3rd
                  Province of Merida, formerly Lugidania [Lusitania] and Galicia, [from] the Algarve
                  to the coasts that bathe in the British Sea - containing Merida, Beja, Baracara,
                  Dumio, Alisbona [Lisbon], Portocale [Porto], Tude, Auria, Luco [Lugo], Astorica
                  [Astorga], Samora, Iria [... onto next page ...]</note></ab>
            <ab>*Porcuna now</ab>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
