<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="zone_Page_91">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.bsr.ac.uk/iiif/2/GELL-VI%2Fwg_06_091.tif/full/full/0/default.jpg"/>
         <zone points="2426,1153 2785,1142 3307,2252 2083,2268" xml:id="zone_Page_91_764d3975-98b3-479b-b959-7edfc6a92100"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain">
            <pb facs="#zone_Page_91" n="091"/>
            <ab>Antequera taken 1410 from Moors. <rs type="person" ref="#king_juseph">Juseph K<hi rend="sueprscript">g</hi> of Granada</rs>
               <sic>succeded</sic> <rs type="person" ref="#mahomet">Mahomet</rs> who died of a poisoned shirt. Ali sent by <rs type="person" ref="#king_juseph">Juseph</rs> to
               <rs type="place" ref="#valladolid"> Valladolid</rs> to K<hi rend="sueprscript">g</hi><rs type="person" ref="#king_donjuan"> Don Juan</rs>, brought horses, velvet,
               raisins, figs almonds but the Queen prevented more truce, for he would not say <rs type="person" ref="xxx">Joseph</rs>
               was vassal of <rs type="place" ref="#spain">Spain</rs> in <date when="1409">1409</date>.</ab>
            <ab><rs type="person" ref="#fernando_aragon">Infante<note type="editorial">A son of the king. In this case, the future Fernando I
               of Aragon, younger son of <rs type="person" ref="#king_donjuan">Juan I of Castile</rs>.</note></rs> came to <rs type="place" ref="#cordoba">Cordova</rs> in feb<hi
                  rend="sueprscript">y</hi>. &amp; besieged Antequera with 10 000 foot &amp; 2500
               horse. <rs type="person" ref="#sancho_rojas">Sancho de Rojas Bishop of Palencia</rs> &amp; <choice>
                  <abbr>C<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></abbr>
                  <expan>Count</expan>
               </choice> <rs type="person" ref="#velasquez">Martin Velasquez</rs>. Kg of Granada sent 5000 horse &amp; 80 000 foot &amp; his
               2 Brothers Cidi Ali &amp; Sidi Hamat but they were beat off, but <rs type="person" ref="#avedano">Martyn Ruys de
               Avedaño</rs> killed by poisoned arrow.</ab>
            <ab>A Real at <rs type="place" ref="#antequera">Antequera</rs>.</ab>
            <metamark/>

            <ab>ill placed old moorish looking town with a ruined castle. Some remains of moorish
               walls. Town composed of high tumbling houses ready for the first earthquake. Gardens
               before it well watered – There had been a Castle &amp; a Royal Palace. It is a
               venerable old ruinous place. Stop about 2 hours for 3 guards there being thieves in
               the way. The people quite ignorant, took us for french which they knew was
               impossible. Hence a very uneven road with some picturesque mills &amp; then a very
               steep ascent with a poor venta<note type="translation">country inn</note>, arrive at
               the top in a cold misty rocky place 1 league &amp; ½ see the sea &amp; descending a
               little a venta<note type="translation">country inn</note>, Venta Nueva a poor place
               the poorest we had seen where sleep. Quit Venta Nueva <date when="1808-12-01">Dec<hi rend="sueprscript"
                  >r</hi> 1<hi rend="sueprscript">st</hi></date> early cold strong wind &amp; mist. Hence 7
               leagues &amp; ¼ to Malaga of which 6 are a steep &amp; winding descent. In the course
               of the first hour the climate changed. A bridge &amp; custom house in about a league
               it became warm, dwarf palms thyme in flower &amp; all the shrubs of the Mediterranean
               coasts. In a short</ab>


            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">In hall of comares 6<hi rend="sueprscript">th</hi>
               “Sutilizaronse las manos del artifice di me tez e lustre, despues de ser adornadas
               las perlas de mi corona e tiara; e parecen en semejanza de aseo decoration<!-- decoration in pencil --> e tribunal
               de esposo, al qual y demas en mi, hay ventaja. porque en mi esta segura la felicidad
               de mi esposo – El, que a mi se allegare con demanda de quitar la sed, en mi hallara
               hartar con licor claro e puro, sin macula ni comistion alguna, E ansi soy semejante
               al arco de la oscuridad que aparece; y el sol de ella es mi Señor Abulhagex: siempre
               luce su palacio seguro como el palacio divino durara abrigo e amparo de los
                  bienaventurados.”<note type="editorial">From <bibl>Antigüedades árabes, vol. 2, p.
                     14.</bibl><note type="translation">The hands of the architect of my [AA: 'de
                     mi'] colour and lustre were made subtle [AA: 'Subtilizáronse'], after the
                     pearls of my crown and tiara were adorned, and they seemed in likeness to the
                     washroom and the husband's court, to which and so forth there is an advantage
                     in me, because in me the happiness of my husband is assured. He who approaches
                     me with a desire to quench his thirst, will find in me plenty [AA: 'hartura']
                     of clear and pure liquor, without any taint or mixture. And so I am like the
                     arc of darkness that appears; and its [the darkness's] sun is my Lord Abulhagex
                     [AA: 'la obscuridad que aparece, y el sol della es mi Señor Abulhachex']: his
                     safe palace always shines as the divine palace will last, shelter and
                     protection of the blessed. </note></note> There was perhaps a fount in this
               hall <metamark>–</metamark> Paseos<note type="editorial"><bibl>Juan de Echeverría,
                     Paseos por Granada y sus contornos..., 2 vols (2nd edn, Granada, 1814).</bibl>
                  WG may equally have been using <bibl>Echeverría's 1764
               original.</bibl></note>.</note>
            <figure type="sketch" facs="#zone_Page_91_764d3975-98b3-479b-b959-7edfc6a92100">
               <note type="editorial_label">Pencil drawing with watercolour: man</note>
               <label>Jew</label>
            </figure>
            <label>Hall of Comares.</label>
            <note type="marginal" facs="xxx">“llevo ventaja à los hermosos con mi amicto y tiara; e
               ansi se declinan a mi los rutilantes luceros del cielo en los signos. Parece en mi el
               agua en manera de religioso, que puesto al medio dia del lugar de su oracion se pone
               a orar: seguras estan por la sucession del tiempo, mis ventajas: mi deseo es hartar
               al que esta sediento, en manera que parece haber yo demostrado esta obra liberal de
               la mano de mi senor Abialhagex. Siempre dure en mi orbe lucero espléndido ansi como
               los luceros del cielo fueron ilustrando la oscura tiniebla.<note type="editorial"
                  >From <bibl>Antigüedades árabes, vol. 2, p. 14.</bibl><note type="translation">I
                     outmatch the beautiful with my amice [vestment worn around neck and shoulders]
                     and tiara; and so the glittering stars in the sky decline to me in the signs.
                     Water seems a kind of devotee to me, which, put at midday in the spot of its
                     prayer, begins to pray: my benefits are safe against the passage of time [AA:
                     'la sucesion de los tiempos']: my desire is to satiate those who thirst, in
                     such a way that I seem to have demonstrated this liberal work by the hand of my
                     lord Abialhagex. May a splendid star always last in my world, like the stars in
                     the sky light up [AA: 'fueren ilustrando'] the gloomy
               darkness.</note></note></note>
            <metamark/>


         </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
