<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="inlet">
            <head> </head>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <div type="spain"> </div>
         <div type="portugal">
            <ab> </ab>
         </div>
         <div type="reading_notes">
            <pb facs="#f-171" n="171"/>
            <fw>34</fw>
            <cb/>
            <note type="editorial">Extracts from/summary of <bibl>Conde, Historia de la dominacion,
                  vol. 1, pp. 30-50.</bibl></note>
            <ab>Sidonia with 90 000 men. The hosts met on a Sunday on banks of the
                     <sic>Guadalede<note type="editorial">i.e. Guadalete</note></sic> 2 days before
                  Ramazan<note type="editorial">Ramadan</note>.<!-- possible anchor --> Temblaba
               debajo de sus pies la tierra y se estremecia, y resonaba el ayre con el estruendo de
               los atambores y añafires y con el sonido di guerreras trompas, y con el espantoso
               alarido de ambas huestes <note type="translation">The earth trembled under their feet
                  and shuddered, and the air rang with the noise of the drummers and trumpets
                  [añafiles] and with the sound of [Conde has 'de'] war trumpets, and with the
                  dreadful howl of both hosts.</note>. 4 Xtians to 1 Turk <note type="editorial"
                  >Conde has 'cuatro Cristianos para cada Muslim' (four Christians for each
                  Muslim)</note> The night separated the armies. Next day the same. Taric on 3<hi
                  rend="superscript">d</hi> day saw the Moors ready to yield so cried G’uala<note
                  type="editorial">i.e. a war cry. Conde gives Taric a much longer speech</note>
               &amp; attacked &amp; killed King Ruderic. &amp; the rest fled. The place covered with
               bones long after. Taric sent Roderics head to Muza. Muza left Africa or Cairvan to
               Abdelaziz his son &amp; brought over 8,000 foot &amp; 10 000 horse. His sons Abdelola
               &amp; Meruan came also, the last gave his name to a palace on the river West of
               Cordova. Came also Arabs of tribe Coraix <note type="editorial">i.e. Quraysh</note>.
               also Almonazir, Aly ben Rebie Lahmi, Hayut ben Reja Tamani, Hanas ben Abdala Asenani,
               <!-- possible anchor -->que despues fue la grande Aljama de Saracusta<note
                  type="translation">who afterwards founded [Conde: fundó] the great Aljama [mosque]
                  of Zaragoza</note>. Taria proceeded in spite of Muza &amp; made good regulations
               for sparing the natives when they submitted. Mugueiz el Rumi went to Cordova. Zayde
               ben Kesadi el Sekseki to Malaga. The third body Taric took by Jayen<note
                  type="editorial">Jaén</note> to Tolaitola or Toledo the capital. Kesadi joined on
               the road having conquered the people of Estija<note type="editorial">Écija</note>.
               Malaga &amp; Elvira yielded.</ab>
            <ab>Spali Esbilia = Sevilla. Mugueiz took Cordoba. Taric at Tolaitola which Capitulated.
               Those who fled lost their goods, those who staid kept all only paying tribute.
               Churches &amp; religion spared only no more to be built without licence. Taric lived
               in the <!-- possible anchor -->alcazar del Rey<note type="translation">the King's
                  fortress</note>. in a room 25 crowns of gold garnished with hyacinths <note
                  type="editorial">i.e. jacinths</note> &amp;other stones. ie one crown for each of
               25 Gothic Kings who had reigned.</ab>
            <ab>Muza went by Esbilia &amp; took it by convention. left Abdila el Towail de Medina
                  <note type="translation">of Medina</note> governor. Thence to Carmuna <note
                  type="editorial">Carmona</note> which yielded. he had 18 000 horse few foot. went
               into Algarbe or Lusitania <note type="editorial">i.e. the south of Portugal</note>
               &amp; took Libla, Ossonoba,</ab>

            <cb/><metamark/>
            <ab>Myrtilis Beja &amp;c &amp; came to Merida a magnif<hi rend="superscript">t</hi> city with high towered
               walls.</ab>
            <ab>Besieged it sent for his Son Abdelaziz with fresh troops. Citizens skirmished with
               loss. Ambuscade by Musa in a deep glen. He takes a tower is driven from it called
               from the deaths Borg Axuhuda = Torre de los Martires <note type="translation">Tower
                  of the Martyrs</note>.</ab>
            <ab>Abdelaziz came with 7,000 horse &amp; ballesteria grande de los Berberies <note
                  type="editorial">Conde has 'gran ballestería': the great crossbowmen of the
                  Berbers</note>. The city yielded. Those who came to the camp saw his long white
               beard one day, it was red black the next. it alarmed them. Found at Merida Roderics
               Queen.</ab>
            <ab>Taric from Tolaitola took a city tras los montes <note type="translation">beyond the
                  mountains</note> &amp; gave it his name. Then Guadilhigiara its river &amp; mount.
               &amp; a Valley Feg Taric. Medina Almeida la mesa de Suleiman <note type="translation"
                  >Suleiman's table</note> because a mesa <note type="translation">table</note>
               garnished with emeralds &amp; jacinths found there. Next Medina Maya where much booty
               &amp; returned to Toledo. Seville rebelled &amp; killed 30 Moors. Abdelaziz sent
               &amp; took it &amp; chastised it. The Roman bridges of Tagus &amp; Guadiana they
               admired much &amp; called Ionian. At Talbera Medina <note type="editorial">Conde has
                  'Medina Talbera'</note> Taric came to meet Musa the Wali &amp; appeased him by
               jewels &amp; spoil &amp; so they went to Toledo. There in the Alcacar <note
                  type="editorial">Fortress (Alcázar)</note> Musa asked for the “mesa de Suleyman
                  <note type="translation">Suleyman's table</note>. It wanted one foot Taric said he
               had found it so. Musa discharged him for disobedience, to his Wali, in the name of
               the Calif.</ab>
            <metamark/>
            <ab>Abdelaziz conquers Tadmir &amp; its Gothic King in Murcia. Tadmir ben Gobdos. At
               Lorca <choice>
                  <abbr>X<hi rend="superscript">ns</hi></abbr>
                  <expan>Christians</expan>
               </choice> defeated in a great battle. X<hi rend="superscript">tians</hi> fled to
               Auriola. The X<hi rend="superscript">n</hi> women mounted guard as men &amp; tied their hair under chins to sham
               beards. Moors taken in. Capitulation. “En nombre de Dios clemente y misericordioso
               Abdelaziz y Tadmir hacen este convenio de paz que Dios confirme y proteja: que Tadmir
               haya el mando de sus gentes, y no otro de los Xtianos de su reyno que no habra entre
               ellos guerra ni se les tomaran cautivos sus hijos ni mugeres: que no serán molestados
               sobre su religion, ni se les incendiarán sus iglesias, sin otros servicios ni
               obligaciones que las aqui convenidas: que esta avenencia se entienda tambien sobre
               siete ciudades, Auriola Valentila, Lecant. Mula. Boscara. Ota y Lorca. que <note
                  type="translation">In the name of God, gracious and merciful, Abdelaziz and Tadmir
                  make this covenant of peace, which God confirms and protects: that Tadmir is in
                  command of his people, and not another of the Christians of his kingdom[:] that
                  there will be no war between them, nor will they take their children or women
                  captive: that they will not be disturbed in their religion, nor will their
                  churches be burned, without other services or obligations than those agreed upon
                  here: that this agreement also be understood for seven cities, Auriola, Valentila,
                  Lecant, Mula, Bocsara, Ota and Lorca. That [onto next page]</note></ab>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="cover">
            <note> </note>
         </div>
         <div type="index"> </div>
      </back>
   </text>

</TEI>
